John Tagliabue Papers
John Tagliabue Papers
1943-1991
Tagliabue, John, 1923-
7.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American poet. Correspondence (1945-1991); journals (1952-1990); notebooks; holograph and typescript poems; articles and reviews.
148696
Biographical History
John Tagliabue (1923-2006) was an American poet and playwright. Born in Italy, Tagliabue came with his family to the United States while still a child. He studied English at Columbia University where his fellow students inluded Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac, and over his career received six Fulbright fellowships which he spent in Italy, China, Japan, and Indonesia. He taught for more than 35 years (1953-1989) at Bates College in Lewiston, Maine, where he actively recruited notable poets like Denise Levertov and Stephen Sender to speak, and where he founded and presided over the "United Nations of Poetry," an informal gathering of students to read the poetry of others and their own work. He is the author of several books of poetry, including New and Selected Poems, 1942-1997 (National Poetry Foundation, 1998).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Tagliabue Papers comprise seventeen series, most of which are self-explanatory:
Correspondence
Correspondence, publicity and reviews
Drama
Essays
Journals
Lists of published work
Miscellaneous
Newspaper clippings
Notebooks
Poetry
Poetry readings
Portrait
Published material
Short stories
Tapes
Thesis
Reviews
Correspondence, publicity and reviews contains material relating to Tagliabue's published books; the folder for The Buddha Uproar contains biographical material. Copies of Tagliabue's published books are located in Published material. Newspaper clippings contains articles of a general nature about Tagliabue and his work, as well as a review of the Mario Puppet Exhibit at Bates College, which included several collaborations between him and his wife, artist Grace Tagliabue.
There are numerous later accessions that have not been processed and are not yet open to researchers. Please contact the repository listed above for more information.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year; Correspondence, publicity and reviews is arranged alphabetically by title. Journals, Notebooks, and Poetry are arranged chronologically by the earliest year according to the groupings established by Tagliabue. Items with a title but no date are arranged alphabetically. Selections with neither a title nor a date are in "Undated" folders.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Tagliabue, John, 1923-; American poetry -- 20th century.; Poets, American.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Manuscripts for publication.; Poems.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1945; 1947-1950,; 1952-1954,; 1958-1959,; 1961-1962,; 1964-1967,; 1969-1976; 24 folders (Box 1)
  - In memory of Mrs. Helen Hirshler, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, publicity and reviews
  - The Buddha Uproar (Box 1)
  - The Doorless Door (Box 1)
  - A Japanese Journal (Box 1)
  - Poems (Box 1)
- Drama
  - Monologue (Box 1)
  - Plays (Box 1)
  - Plays for Voices (Box 1)
  - Puppet Plays, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Tragedy (Box 1)
  - Translation (Box 1)
- Essays
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Journals
  - Holograph
    - 1952, Paris (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1958, Summer tour of Europe (Box 1)
    - 1964, Greek, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1968, Brazil and Peru (Box 1)
    - 1971, Venice (Box 1)
  - Typescript
    - 1945-1946, Lebanese (Box 1)
    - 1946-1947, Pullman, Washington, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948, New York, Selections (Box 1)
    - 1948-1950, Alfred (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952, Italy (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952, Summer in Paris and London (Box 1)
    - 1952, Paris (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1956, Mexico (Box 1)
    - 1956-1957, Maine, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1958, Summer tour of Europe (Box 1)
    - 1962, Spain (Box 2)
    - 1964, Greek, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972, italy (Box 2)
    - 1974, Mostly Anatolia (Box 2)
    - 1975, Maine (Box 2)
    - The Adriatic and Sicily in the Wrong Season (Box 2)
    - The Train Ride Between Pisa and Florence (Box 2)
- Lists of published work
  - Various (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Notebooks
  - Holographs
    - Noh (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959, January-April (Box 2)
    - 1959, May-July (Box 2)
    - 1959, July-October (Box 2)
    - 1965 (Box 2)
    - 1965, Summer (Box 2)
    - 1972, February-March (Box 2)
    - 1972, March-April (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Typescripts
    - Androscoggin accounts (Box 2)
    - Kabuki (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Shakespeare, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Teacher's notebook, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Writer's workshop (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1977, Bardwell Street (Box 2)
- Poetry
  - Holographs
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1962, suggested by Shakespeare (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1964, General (Box 3)
    - 1964, Poems for Grace (Box 3)
    - 1965, General (Box 3)
    - 1965, Summer in France (Box 3)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969, some earlier (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1971, General (Box 3)
    - 1970-1971, Poems Related to My Father (Box 3)
    - 1971-1972, Italy
      - General (Box 3)
      - Venice
        - General (Box 3)
        - Saint George Series (Box 3)
        - Santa Maria della Salute (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
  - Typescripts
    - 1940-1950, No Skating Please (Box 3)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 3)
    - 1941-1946 (Box 3)
    - 1941-1948 (Box 3)
    - 1941-1951 (Box 3)
    - 1943-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1946-1952, Lyrics and The Jungle (Box 3)
    - 1949-1950, Alfred, N.Y. (Box 3)
    - 1950-1952, General (Box 3)
    - 1950-1952, The Italy Poems (Box 3)
    - 1952-1953, The Ischia Poems and Island, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1953-1954, The Erica Collection (Box 3)
    - 1954 (Box 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1962, A Japanese Journal, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961, The Antics of the Alphabet (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961, General (Box 4)
    - 1960-1966 [?] (Box 4)
    - 1962-1965, Cities in the Dearth of the Cold War (Box 4)
    - 1963, Buon Natale (Box 4)
    - 1964, Poems for Grace (Box 4)
    - 1965, Poems for Grace (Box 4)
    - 1965, Summer in France (Box 4)
    - 1966, Christmas (Box 4)
    - 1966, General (Box 4)
    - 1967, General (Box 4)
    - 1967, Spain (Box 4)
    - 1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969, some earlier (Box 4)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970 (Box 4)
    - 1970 July, A Provincial Plus a New York Poodle (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971, General (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971, Poems Related to My Father (Box 4)
    - 1971-1972, Italy Poems (Complete) (Box 4)
    - 1971-1972, Italy Poems (Selections) (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
    - The Animal Poems (Box 4)
    - The Buddha Uproar (Box 4)
    - Centering (Box 4)
    - At the Circus and the Fair (Box 4)
    - A Greek Cousin (Box 4)
    - Insects (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Noh (Box 4)
    - Scribbling as the Air Shakes, and, A Walking Tour of Shikoku (Box 4)
    - The Twelve Months (Box 4)
    - Zen and the Teaching of Poetry (Box 4)
- Poetry Readings
  - Announcements (Box 4)
  - Introductions (Box 4)
- Portrait
  - Portrait (Box 4)
- Published material
  - Bates Anthology (Box 4)
  - Bennett College Journal (Box 4)
  - Books, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper (Box 4)
  - Poems in Little Magazines (Box 4)
  - "Viaje a Mexico" (Box 4)
- Short stories
  - Undated (Box 4)
  - Prior to 1947 (Box 4)
  - Prior to 1947 (Box 5)
- Tapes
  - From Poems, 4 tapes (Box 5)
  - Mario Plays, 6 tapes (Box 5)
  - Other readings, 2 tapes (Box 5)
- Thesis
  - Thesis (Box 5)
- Reviews
  - Reviews by Tagliabue (Box 5)